Albert Tian Chen

Interdisciplinary student researcher with 3+ years of statistics, data science and visualization experience, as well as a coursework foundation in biology and the basic sciences. Attending graduate school to apply both wet and dry lab techniques towards studies of molecular biology and systems biology.

Phone: 339-927-0113

Email: <u>chen.alb@northeastern.edu</u>

Portfolio: https://atchen.me

GitHub: https://github.com/blahoink

ORCID ID: <u>0000-0002-5387-0208</u>

LinkedIn: https://linkedin.com/in/achen339

EDUCATION

Northeastern University, *College of Engineering*, Boston, MA Candidate for Bachelor of Science in *Bioengineering*

9/2015 – Present Expected 2020

• 3.7 / 4.0 GPA, 3.8 / 4.0 Major Courses GPA

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Vector Engineering Team, Broad Institute of MIT and Harvard (Link)

Research Assistant, Cambridge MA

5/2019 - Present

- With a <u>Broad Shark Tank-winning team</u>, accelerate discovery of promising recombinant adenoassociated viruses (AAV) for gene therapy in the central nervous system, by developing a novel computational method of identifying functional variants from large screens of randomized gene libraries
- Mine complex atomic interactions in AAV capsid proteins with PyMOL scripts, and visualize them in an interactive application built with Python and Bokeh
- Build a user-friendly and code-free data processing pipeline for next-generation sequencing data, and store/query results with PostgreSQL, using the Google Cloud Platform

Slavov Laboratory, Northeastern University (Link)

Research Assistant, Boston MA

7/2016 - Present

- First author on <u>DART-ID</u> project, a Bayesian framework for increasing peptide identification rates in mass-spec proteomics experiments, by incorporating peptide retention time as additional evidence.
- Co-first author on <u>DO-MS</u>, a modular, extensible, and automated data analysis and visualization platform for rationally optimizing mass spectrometry methods
- Design and run LC/MS single cell proteomics experiments, from cell culture to instrument operation, with the Single Cell Proteomics by Mass Spectrometry (SCoPE-MS) method (http://scope2.slavovlab.net/)

Waters Corporation, Separations R&D

Chemistry Co-op, Milford MA

7/2017 - 12/2017

- Prototyped high-throughput LC/MS analysis workflow that doubled throughput to 4800 samples/day, through hardware and firmware modifications to existing instrumentation
- Implemented efficient low-level data processing software in C++ and Armadillo
- Performed maintenance, repairs, and installed custom modifications on Acquity LC instruments and Waters mass spectrometry instruments

PUBLICATIONS

Chen AT, Franks A, Slavov N (2019) DART-ID increases single-cell proteome coverage. PLOS

Computational Biology 15(7): e1007082. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1007082

Website: https://dart-id.slavovlab.net/

Chen AT*, Huffman RG*, Specht H*, Slavov N (2019) DO-MS: Data-Driven Optimization of Mass

Spectrometry Methods. *Journal of Proteome Research* 18(6): 2493-2500. https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jproteome.9b00039. * Co-first authors

Website: https://do-ms.slavovlab.net/

AWARDS / FELLOWSHIPS

Summer Scholars Independent Research Fellowship, Northeastern University (\$5000)	2019
Advanced Research/Creative Endeavor Award, Northeastern University (\$3000)	2018
ASBMB Active Site Poster / Travel Award Winner	2018
Bioengineering Research Achievement Award, Northeastern University	2018
Dean's Merit Scholarship	2015 – Present
Dean's List	2015 – Present

Applied To:

NSF GRFP – 3 years support, \$34K/year stipend, \$12K/year tuition

NDSEG - 3 years support, \$38.4K/year stipend, full tuition and fees, \$1.2K/year insurance, \$5K travel

DOE CSGF - Up to 4 years support, \$37K/year stipend, full tuition and fees, \$5K academic allowance

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Programming:

Advanced: Python, R, JavaScript, HTML/CSS Proficient: MATLAB, LaTEX, SQL, bash, C

Software / Libraries:

numpy, pandas, bokeh, STAN, shiny, dplyr, matplotlib, ggplot, git, Google Cloud Platform (Compute Engine, Storage, SQL), Adobe Photoshop, Adobe Illustrator

Laboratory:

Mammalian Cell Culture, Proteomics Sample Prep, LC/MS operation + maintenance

Hands-On:

Shop and Hand Tools, Basic Bench Electronic Equipment, Computer Building and Repair

OTHER EXPERIENCE

Journal of Medical Insight (JOMI), Lead Web Developer, Boston MA

6/2014 - 9/2016

- Led development of http://old.jomi.com with no prior web development experience, in 3 months
- Rebuilt site in Node.js, MongoDB, and React as https://jomi.com a year later, again in 3 months
- Assisted in filming live surgeries with video team

Bikeway Source, Sales Associate/Bike Mechanic, Bedford MA

8/2012 - 6/2014

Performed bike repair, facility construction, sales, and customer service

PRESENTATIONS

Poster: <u>Chen AT</u>, Chan YA, Deverman BE, Elzahraa-Eid F. Clustif: Motif-based clustering of short peptides for protein engineering applications. Presented at 15th annual Broad Retreat (Broad Institute of MIT and Harvard), December 2019, Boston MA

PDF: https://atchen.me/images/clustif_poster_v10.pdf

Poster: <u>Chen AT</u>, Perlman DH, Emmott E, Huffman RG & Slavov N. P-SCOPE: Carrier-enabled low-input phosphoproteomics by mass spectrometry. Presented at American Society of Biochemistry and Molecular Biology (ASBMB) Active Site Northeast Regional Meeting, November 2019, Boston MA

PDF: https://atchen.me/images/PSCOPE poster v2.pdf

Poster: <u>Chen AT</u>, Perlman DH, Emmott E, Huffman RG & Slavov N. P-SCOPE: Carrier-enabled low-input phosphoproteomics by mass spectrometry. Presented at Northeastern University Creative Endeavor and Research Experience Symposium (CERES), October 2019, Boston MA

PDF: https://atchen.me/images/NUSPURF Vertical 2019.pdf

Poster: <u>Chen AT</u>, Perlman DH, Emmott E, Huffman RG & Slavov N. P-SCOPE: Carrier-enabled low-input phosphoproteomics by mass spectrometry. Presented at Northeastern Bioengineering Research Symposium, June 2019, Boston MA

PDF: https://atchen.me/images/PSCOPE poster v1.pdf

Presentation: Chen AT, Franks A & Slavov N. DART-ID Increases Single-Cell Proteome Coverage.

Presented at Single Cell Proteomics (SCP) Conference, June 2019, Boston MA

Video: https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=IWeasIXs5F0 Slides: https://atchen.me/images/DART_SCP_v3.pptx

Poster: <u>Chen AT</u>, Franks A & Slavov N. DART-ID Increases Single-Cell Proteome Coverage. Presented at Experimental Biology (EB) as part of the American Society of Biochemistry and Molecular Biology (ASBMB), April 2019, Orlando FL

PDF: https://atchen.me/images/DART_poster_v6.pdf

Poster: <u>Chen AT</u>, Franks A & Slavov N. DART-ID Increases Single-Cell Proteome Coverage. Presented at Northeastern Research, Innovation, and Scholarship Expo (RISE), April 2019, Boston MA PDF: https://atchen.me/images/DART_RISE Poster.pdf

Poster: <u>Chen AT</u>, Franks A & Slavov N. DART-ID Increases Proteome Coverage with Data-Driven Alignment of Retention Times. Presented at American Society of Biochemistry and Molecular Biology (ASBMB) Active Site Northeast Regional Meeting, November 2018, Boston MA

PDF: https://atchen.me/images/dart_poster_v2_3.pdf

Poster: <u>Chen AT</u>, Franks A & Slavov N. DART-ID Data-Driven Alignment of Retention Times for Peptide Identification increases peptide coverage by 75%. Presented at Single Cell Proteomics (SCP) Conference, June 2018, Boston MA

PDF: https://atchen.me/images/scp_poster_v6.pdf

RELEVANT COURSEWORK

Biology:

Molecular Engineering, Cellular Engineering, Tissue Engineering, Genetics and Molecular Biology

Chemistry:

Organic Chemistry 1 & 2, Biochemistry

Math / Statistics:

Supervised Machine Learning (Audited), Unsupervised Machine Learning (Audited), Dynamic Modeling in Systems Biology, Differential Equations, Statistics (MIT OCW 18.05), Linear Algebra (MIT OCW 18.06)

Physics:

Physics 1 & 2, Statics and Dynamics, Transport and Fluids, Circuits and Signal Processing